<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Irenicum, or, An essay for union wherein are humbly tender'd some proposals in order to some nearer union amongst the godly of different judgments / by Mr. Samuel Mather ...</title>
            <author>Mather, Samuel, 1626-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7678</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12990659</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12990659</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96320</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96320)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 390:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Irenicum, or, An essay for union wherein are humbly tender'd some proposals in order to some nearer union amongst the godly of different judgments / by Mr. Samuel Mather ...</title>
                  <author>Mather, Samuel, 1626-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Snowden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian union --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96320:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96320:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IRENICUM:</hi> OR AN ESSAY FOR UNION. WHEREIN Are Humbly Tender'd ſome propoſals in order to ſome nearer Union amongſt the Godly of different Judgments.</p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>SAMUEL MATHER,</hi> Lately Paſtor of a Church of Chriſt in <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Quia conjungi poſſunt voluntates hominum in bono, quamvis omni ex parte non habent ſenſus conſentientes circa illa quae, pertinent ad bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num quod appetunt, idcirco diſſenſio opinionum circa illa quae minus ſunt neceſſaria, quamvis perfectionem concordiae impediat, ipſi tamen concordiae non repugnat,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Philip. 3.15, 16.</hi> Ameſ. Caſ. Conſe. lib. <hi>5.</hi> Cap. <hi>29.</hi> Theſ. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Neceſſarium eſt ſtudium concordiae. <hi>1.</hi> ratione charitatis a qua fluit, &amp; quam fovet, promovet &amp; implet. <hi>2.</hi> ratione Juſtitiae cujus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedimenta removet. <hi>3.</hi> ratione felicitatis tam communis quam pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatae, quae unitis viribus concordium bonorum facilius procuratur <bibl>Idem Eod. Cap.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Opinionum varietas &amp; opinantium unitas non ſunt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Boroughs of Heart diviſions.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Siquid noviſti rectius iſtis.</l>
               <l>Candidus imperti, ſi non, his utere mecum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Snowden.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96320:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96320:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>IRENICUM:</hi> OR AN ESSAY for UNION. WHEREIN Are humbly tender'd ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals in order to a Nearer Union amongſt thoſe of Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Judgments.</head>
            <p>THoſe who have appeared ſtudious of reformation in theſe Nations, have been unhappily ſubdivided into three Forms or Parties, Commonly known by the names of <hi>Presbyterians, Independents,</hi> and <hi>Anti-paedo-Baptiſts.</hi> Under each of which there be ſome who are judged by thoſe that differ from them, to be truly Godly, and to have the root of the matter in them, as holding Chriſt the Head under theſe various Forms. Who being not yet united into one mind and Judgment, by conviction of error and miſtake in thoſe things
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96320:3"/>wherein they differ, which nevertheleſs as we have ſeen through the Free-Grace of Chriſt, ſome inſtances of already, ſo we may hope for in ſome further meaſure, when thoſe better times ſhall come, whereof the Lord hath ſaid that he will give his People <hi>one heart, and one way:</hi> Mean while it may not be amiſs, to try how near we can come together, ſuppoſing each party to remain uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of any error in their way.</p>
            <p>Now in order to this end it will be requiſite to Conſider concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe three Judgments.</p>
            <p>Firſt how far they agree. And then,</p>
            <p>Wherein they differ. And then,</p>
            <p>To make ſome propoſals in order to ſome nearer and cloſer Union amongſt them. Unto which Method we are led not out of any deſire or delight to revive the mention of our differences, which we could wiſh had been prevented, or could now be buryed in everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſilence and oblivion: But becauſe they are ſo publick that they cannot be hid, and becauſe we are perſuaded that a great part of our diviſions hath ariſen from miſunderſtandings of one another, and we cannot well proceed, or not with any great clearneſs and evidence of light, but rather as men groping in the dark to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound means and ways of Union, nor can we paſs any juſt and well grounded Judgment upon what is propounded, if we do not in ſome meaſure underſtand and rightly apprehend the true State of the Controverſies; therefore let us conſider one another to provoke un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Love and to good Works.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Agreements.</head>
               <p>Firſt Then, for the Agreements, they may be referred to four General Heads.</p>
               <p>Firſt, We do agree in the Fundamentals of Doctrine, in the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, as alſo in the Rules of a Chriſtian Life; that this is ſo doth appear as by other Evidences, ſo by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring together the ſeveral Confeſſions of Faith. That of the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> was approved and accepted in the ſame words both by the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the year 1647. And ſo far as concerns matters of Faith or Doctrine, by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>New-England</hi> alſo, as they have declared in the Preface to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96320:3"/>their Platform of Diſcipline, Publiſhed in the Year 1648. As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the great Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> in the ſame Year 1648. And finally by the Congregational Churches in <hi>England</hi> in their general meeting at the <hi>Savoy Anno</hi> 1658. And the Confeſſion of the Churches of the <hi>Anti-paedo-Baptiſts</hi> in <hi>London</hi> Publiſhed (<hi>circiter</hi>) 1650. Though not in the ſame Form of Words, yet upon peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of it, we cannot ſay there is any fundamental difference appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as to the ſubſtance of the matter of Doctrine, held forth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>If any objection be made concerning any particular Perſons, as to fundamental unſoundneſs and Corruption of Judgment, or looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unholineſs of Converſation. The Anſwer is, that there be ſome, yea, we hope many under each of theſe denominations, unto whom God of his Grace hath given the Spirit of a ſound mind, and a Converſation adorning the Doctrine of God our Saviour. But men of Corrupt minds not holding the Head, but holding damnable Hereſies that are <hi>Devoratoria ſalutis,</hi> are not included nor intended in theſe Propoſals, no more than men of prophane lives. If there be any Perſons or Societies either under theſe or any other Forms or ways of profeſſion whatſoever, who do not agree in the fundamentals of the Chriſtian Faith, or do not live Chriſtian lives, doubtleſs the Lord doth not call his People to unite with ſuch, but to bear witneſs againſt them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This agreement in Faith and Holineſs infers and carries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it all the Duties of Charity and Chriſtian Love, as Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy and Compaſſion towards the Saints in all their Sufferings and Afflictions, to relieve their wants and ſtreights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> duties to be performed towards all, even to Enemies and the worſt of men, when their neceſſities call for it, but more eſpecially towards the Houſhold of Faith, even to all the Saints, though differing, though erring in ſome leſſer thing. Hither belongs a candid conſtruction of all their actions and notions, interpreting every thing to the beſt ſence, not taking an eſtimate of any whole party of Profeſſors from ſome few inconſiderable Individuals, nor calculating the whole from the perſonal miſcarriages of ſome, bearing with the infirmities of the weak, forbearing and avoiding unbrotherly and provoking terms and words, with many other things of the like nature, all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96320:4"/>which are the neceſſary effects and fruits of Cordial and Chriſtian Love.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As to the matters of God's Worſhip: There is an Agreement ſo far as concerns the main Acts of natural Worſhip in the firſt Commandment <hi>viz.</hi> Prayer, Preaching, and hearing the Word, as alſo in the ſpecial time of publick Worſhip, the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, for we all obſerve that day, and there is no ſcruple made of joyning together in Prayer and Preaching, and hearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which accordingly is ordinarily practiſed amongſt us in this City. Which as it is ſome further ſtep towards Love and Union, ſo we have cauſe alſo to acknowledge it to the Lord, as a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Advance and increaſe of Light ſhining forth upon us in theſe preſent times, for it was a thing much ſcrupled in the former Age before the late Reformation by ſome whoſe Name and Sect hath diſappeared, being worn out by the further progreſs of the Light and Work of Chriſt amongſt us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As to matters of Inſtitution and Church-Worſhip, in the Second Commandment, here indeed it is that the difference lies, but yet there be ſome General Agreements even here alſo, at leaſt in the Fundamentals of Worſhip. Inſtance may be given in Four Uniting Principles ſufficient for a ſafe and well grounded Union.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We all agree that the Scripture is the Rule as in all other matters of Faith and Life, ſo likewiſe in the matters of God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Lord hath appointed a Miniſtery in his Church, who are bound by their Office to Preach the Word, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Seals and Cenſures in his name.</p>
               <p>That the Lord's Supper ought not to be adminiſtred promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly unto all,
<note place="margin">Confeſſi. Faith. Cap. 30. of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, propos. 4.</note> but <q>All Ignorant and ungodly Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as they are unfit to enjoy Communion with Chriſt, ſo they are unworthy of the Lord's Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and cannot without great ſin againſt him, whil'ſt they remain ſuch, partake of theſe Holy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96320:4"/>Myſteries, or be admitted thereunto:</q> This is a Truth of ſo great weight and evidence, that both <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> have thought fit to inſert it, in their Confeſſion of Faith. And it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in that Article of the Creed, the Communion of Saints. Yea the Epiſcopal Party hath born witneſs to it:
<note place="margin">See the 39 Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Art. 27.</note>
                  <q>For they do affirm that the Viſible Church is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Faithful Men (therefore not of debauched Perſons) where the Word of Chriſt is duely Preached, and the Sacraments be rightly Miniſtred.</q> And at the ordination of Miniſters they require a promiſe of them to exerciſe the Diſcipline of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">In the form of ordering Prieſts as Deacons.</note> And if it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired what this Diſcipline is, they thus expreſs their notion of it. <q>In the primitive Church (ſay they,) there was a godly Diſcipline,
<note place="margin">Books of Com. Prayer, Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat againſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> that at the beginning of Lent, ſuch perſons as were noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſinners, were put to open pennance and puniſhed in this World that their Souls might be ſaved in the day of the Lord; and that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers admoniſhed by their example might be the more afraid to offend. In the ſtead whereof, until the ſaid Diſcipline may be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red again, (which thing is much to be wiſhed) it is thought good that in your preſence be read the General Sentences of God's curſing againſt impenitent ſinners, and that ye ſhould anſwer to every Sentence, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Yet further they order Miniſters thus to act in the admiſſion of Perſons to the Lord's Supper.
<note place="margin">Rubrick before the Communion.</note>
                  <q>If any (ſay they) be an open and notorious evil Liver, ſo that the Congregation by him is offended, or have done any wrong to his Neighbours by word or deed, the Curate having knowledge thereof, ſhall call him and advertiſe him in any wiſe not to preſume to come to the Lord's Table, until he have openly declared himſelf to have truly repented and amended his former naughty life, that the Congregation may thereby be ſatisfied, which afore were offended. The ſame order ſhall the Curate uſe with thoſe betwixt whom he perceiveth malice and hatred to reign, not ſuffering them to be partakers of the Lord's Table until he know them to be reconciled. The Miniſter ought to admit the penitent Perſon to the Holy Communion, and not him that is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96320:5"/>obſtinate.</q> Thus fully, thus expreſly do even Epiſcopal men own and bear witneſs to this Truth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There is this further Agreement, that the Ceremonies and other Epiſcopal Inventions in the worſhip of God are ſinful and unlawful. Upon this Account, and in the Teſtimony of this truth, it is that we are all fellow ſufferers and Brethren in Affliction at this day, under the Prelates who by their violence againſt us for the Truth and Teſtimony of theſe times, as well as by their Compliance with <hi>Rome</hi> and other evils, but chiefly by their Aſſiduity, in that good work of ſilencing Godly Miniſters and impoſing upon tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, do manifeſtly declare what Intereſt and what Spirit they are of, and how uncapable and unwilling to unite with us.</p>
               <p>There may be perſonal Love and Honour, due to ſome Individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als amongſt them, eſpecially to ſome who lived in former darker times before the day broke out upon them, and were indued with another and a better ſpirit than uſually appeareth and looketh out in that form, <hi>Even the Spirit of a ſound mind,</hi> and a good life, and brotherly love and tenderneſs towards tender Conſciences: There is Chriſtian Love and eſteem due to ſuch, as perſonally and individual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, and we ſhould be willing and ready to receive and unite with them in the Lord. As neither do we judge every Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual in the external Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> But of the whole Bulk and body of them in their preſent Intereſt and Conſtitution, as alſo of the form it ſelf as Complexly conſidered with all that is involved in the Bowels of it, there is not the ſame Reaſon.</p>
               <p>But thus far in theſe four particulars at leaſt, there ſeemeth to be a general Concurrence and Conſent amongſt the whole reforming Party, even in the matters of inſtituted Worſhip.</p>
               <p>Secondly, And as for thoſe Inquiries, what ſhall then be done for Union with ſuch whoſe way of Worſhip doth exclude the Scripture and the Miniſtry, and who make promiſcuous adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Superſtitious Ceremonies, the condition of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, Beſides what hath been already hinted, we ſay further,</p>
               <p>That the Scripture and the Miniſtry are things too precious to be parted with, for Union with any ſort of men whatſoever, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96320:5"/>the ſame we muſt needs ſay concerning the Chriſtian Sabbath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned. Moreover Communion with Scandalous Perſons, and Conformity to the Ceremonies and Superſtitious Vanities, are ſuch hard conditions of Church Communion as cannot with a ſafe Conſcience be accepted of. Therefore we humbly judge that the beſt expreſſion of our Love to men of ſuch Principles, and the beſt way and means for Union with them is this, to labour to reduce them and bring them off from the error of their way, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for that it is attended and accompanied uſually with looſneſs and prophanneſs, which whil'ſt they do perſiſt and continue in, and that in a day of ſo clear Goſpel Light, and Liberty, as through Grace theſe Nations have injoyed, it may well become all the People of God to ſay, <hi>O my Soul come not thou into their ſecret, and unto their Aſſembly, my glory be not thou united.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have therefore omitted in this Eſſay for Union amongſt thoſe People of God, all ſuch dead and blaſted forms, out of which God is gone, and which are but ſtreams and rivulets as it were of that dead Sea, <hi>that Sea of Blood the Fiſh whereof dyeth.</hi> Rev. 8.8, 9. and Chap. 16.3. <hi>Not of that Chriſtal Sea.</hi> Rev. 4.6. <hi>Lively Images of the Beaſt.</hi> Rev. 13.14, 15. <hi>Thoſe names of men, and not of God's appointing.</hi> Rev. 11.13. <hi>Plants which our Heavenly Father never Planted in his Church.</hi> Mat. 15.13. And which therefore in times and places of Reformation have been pluckt up, and caſt forth, to the rejoycing of the upright in heart.</p>
               <p>Thus much for the Agreements amongſt the Reforming Parties.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Differences.</head>
               <p>Now for the matters in Difference, we mean ſtill amongſt thoſe that ſeem to have their faces <hi>Sion</hi> ward, and to be ſtudious of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. Truely to conſider what they are, may even make us aſhamed of our diviſions, that ever ſo great offences and diſtances in affection ſhould ariſe from ſo ſmall differences in opinion.</p>
               <p>And Firſt, between the <hi>Ptesbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Independents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There be ſome Controverſies ſprung up between them of ſuch a nature, as we do not judge it neceſſary to the preſent purpoſe, and ſcope of this paper largely to inſiſt thereon. Whereof we may inſtance in three ſorts, or kinds of Queſtions.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96320:6"/>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe which ſeem to be rather Speculative, and in Logical terms than practical, which, unleſs Satan and Corruption have the managing of them, are not likely much to obſtruct or ſtand in the way of this ſo much deſired Union. As, for inſtance, that acute Queſtion concerning the Univerſal Viſible Church, which though the right notion of it gives a light and influence into the whole buſineſs of Church Diſcipline, and there is ſome diſcrepancy in the notions and apprehenſions of Godly Learned Men about it, yet while the denying of the Univerſal Viſible Church, is not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the denying of Communion of Churches, nor yet the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it improved to the denying of particular Churches, ſo as to make Godly People <hi>lye among the pots,</hi> and live at a looſe end, <hi>as Lambs in a large place,</hi> under no particular Paſtoral charge, under no ſpecial overſight and inſpection for their ſouls: whil'ſt both ſides do acknowledge both in their judgment and practice, not only the Univerſal inviſible Church, about which there is no Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, but alſo particular Churches, and Communion of Churches, not only ſpiritual and myſtical Communion by the ſame Spirit of Faith and Love, dwelling and working in them all, but alſo Viſible Communion in the ordinances and outward diſpenſations of his Grace, all this may well ſuffice unto brotherly Love and Union. There is alſo ſome further diſpute about this word (Church) about the Application of it to a whole Nation. Where Chriſtianity hath obtained a Civil ſanction and eſtabliſhment in the Laws of the Land, as in thoſe we call Chriſtian States or Kingdoms, but if ſuch a Kingdom be called a National Church, the matter is not great, if withal it be remembred and acknowledged, that Chriſt hath not tyed his Ordinances under the New Teſtament to any one place, as of old to the Temple, but hath appointed them to be diſpenſed in the ſeveral Congregations, and Aſſemblies of his people. Theſe and other ſuch like Queſtions, though they may and ought to be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſearched into, for every <hi>Apex</hi> of truth is precious, the leaſt <hi>Jota</hi> thereof is not to be deſpiſed, as the very filings and duſt of Gold is precious, yet being rather in terms and notions, and not ſo directly Practical, and Theological, as there is no juſt reaſon, ſo we hope in the Lord there is no great danger, they ſhould diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and diſunite the Spirits of Godly learned and ſober men, who are acted and influenced by the Spirit and grace of Chriſt in their debates and diſquiſitions.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96320:6"/>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe things alſo are not of preſent Conſideration, which are the Judgement rather of particular Perſons, than of the whole Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. As to give ſome few inſtances of many: Ordination of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors at large, and before Election <hi>ad Miniſterium vagum or ſine ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo,</hi> which our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as well as of <hi>New-England</hi> doe not approve, though nevertheleſs they that do, if in all other things without exception, muſt be owned and numbred amongſt the Lord's faithful Miniſters, becauſe they Miniſter to him and to his People in the Goſpel of his Son. Moreover it is granted by all that it is no way fit, men ſhould ſend themſelves and run upon their own heads into the Miniſtery, but that they go forth unto that work by the judgment and encouragement of Godly Faithful Miniſters of more ability and experience than themſelves, <hi>For the Spirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets;</hi> who if they ſolemnly ſeek the Lord in prayer with them and for them, there can be no hurt in that. And if withal they lay their hands upon them, this cannot be matter of much offence to any. So that in the Iſſue all the difference remaining as to this point, is not about their paſſing through miniſterial Tryal and approbation, but only about impowring them to Baptize and Adminiſter the Sacraments in an unfixed way without any ſpecial relation to a particular flock or charge; for to Preach the Goſpel, if they do attend upon that work as their particular Calling is generally granted to be lawful, and is ordinarily practiſed without offence, and to the good of Souls, by thoſe we call <hi>Lecturers:</hi> Hither alſo not impertinently as not being the unanimous Judgment of any whole party, may be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the reaſonings which have made ſo great a noiſe about <hi>Pariſh Precincts,</hi> which though ſome perhaps do religiouſly obſerve, and bind up themſelves unto, yet there be others under every form, who make no ſcruple to tranſgreſs them. For not only the <hi>Independents</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> but the very <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Prelate-Proteſtants</hi> have thought it lawful in the late times to receive thoſe of their way from all the Pariſhes round about, who likewiſe have made no ſcruple to attend upon their miniſtry, and Communicate in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances with them in their own way, when moſt of the publick places were in other hands. Whereby it may ſeem that no ſort or ſect of Chriſtians at this day, in theſe Nations, do judge themſelves neceſſarily involved in Church-Communion by their habitation.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96320:7"/>However a Church, according to the Scripture being a Spiritual Body or Society, and the limits being part of the Eſſence or Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of ſuch a Body, that therefore they muſt be Spiritual and of the ſame nature, and not meerly humane as, is the diviſion of Pariſhes is a notion which hath ſo great an appearance of Spiritual reaſon, that there muſt needs be a great meaſure of brotherly kindneſs and indulgence due to ſuch as act upon it, if in all other things they walk without offence. Hither alſo laſtly may be referred, and ſo let them be diſmiſſed and forgotten whatever unbrotherly reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and changes of Schiſme or Antichriſtianiſme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may have been uſed by ſome particular men of harſh and violent Spirits, but not approved by others of the ſame judgment, being men of wiſer and cooler Spirits.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Third ſort of Queſtions not to be now inſiſted on is, the unhappy differences that have fallen out about State-matters, the effects whereof we feel at this day, which are and muſt be left quietly and peaceably with the Lord, and wherein perhaps we may all ſtand in ſome need of pardon and forgiveneſs, not only from God, but from one another. But the debate and diſcuſſion of all ſuch things, and how to accommodate them, may be waved for the preſent, as either not very momentous, or not ſeaſonable, or not likely to be much conducing to the preſent ſcope, which is healing and reuniting the Spirits of good men.</p>
               <p>We find then the remaining differences which ſeem to require a preſent and more particular conſideration, conſiſt chiefly in three Things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That from whence they have their reſpective denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is about Claſſes and Synods. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> conceiving as it is expreſſed by the Provincial Aſſembly of <hi>London,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jus div.</hi> C. 14. P. 240.</note>
                  <q>That Jeſus Chriſt hath laid down in his word a pattern of a Synod, yea of a Juridical Synod conſiſting of Governing Officers of divers Presbyterial Churches. The Congregational Men on the contrary hold,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ames Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw, Eng.</hi> Pur. C. 2. Th. 3.</note> that Jeſus Chriſt hath not ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any Church or Congregation of his to any other ſuperior Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction than
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96320:7"/>unto that which is within itſelf, ſo that if a whole Church of Congregation ſhall err in any matters of Faith or Religion, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church or Spiritual Church Officers, have by any warrant from the Word of God, power to cenſure, puniſh or controul the ſame, but only to Counſel and adviſe them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now that this difference may not appear greater than indeed it is, we may do well to conſider the Conceſſions on both ſides.</p>
               <p>For Firſt we find that our Brethren of the Presbytery on the one ſide grant that a Church in an <hi>Iſland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. Aſſ. <hi>Lond. Jus. div.</hi> C. 15. P. 251.</note> or in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Country where it cannot conveniently aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, muſt not be denyed intireneſs of Juriſdiction within itſelf. The Congregational Brethren on the other ſide grant the lawfulneſs and uſefulneſs of Synods in the Church of God,
<note place="margin">See the Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getical narrat.</note> and the accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs of particular Congregations thereunto. The abſolute unaccountableneſs whereof they do, even with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting expreſſions diſclaim. So that when things are throughly examined, all the difference remaining as to this head ſeemeth to be only about the beſt way for regulation of Synods. For the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational men would have them to be Elective and occaſional, not ſtanding and permanent, and to go no further than the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move beyond the particular Congregation, but the ſubordination of Synods one unto another in greater and leſſer Aſſemblies they ſtick at. And towards an erring Church they would not have them to put forth a formal act of Cenſure or excommunication, but only a ſentence of non-Communion, whereby the difference is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a very narrow point, ſurely not wide enough to be a juſt Cauſe for breach of Love and diſtance of affection amongſt Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
               <p>Yea ſo near do theſe two Forms come together, and ſo narrow is the parting point that ſome of the Presbyterian judgment have ſaid,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Marſhal,</hi> Serm. on <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4.</note>
                  <q>They grant that which doth <hi>tantamount,</hi> and they differ but in ſome leſſer things, and this diſagreement (ſay they) ſhall not hinder us from any Chriſtian accord with them in affection.</q>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. aſſ. <hi>Jus div.</hi> miniſt. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Independents</hi> reciprocally profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be for <q>
                     <hi>a tender Presbytery.</hi>
                  </q> And that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96320:8"/>ſuch is that of the Churches in <hi>New-England:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>H. P.</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice <hi>prope fin.</hi>
                  </note> And ſo deſirous of Union with their Brethren and ſo loth to differ, that ſome of the firſt who have appeared in that cauſe do approve and cloſe with him;
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>R. M.</hi> Ans. to Mr. <hi>C. H.</hi>
                  </note> they anſwer, in drawing down the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences to the narroweſt compaſs, and they write as do others generally of the ſame Judgment, in a moderate and Brotherly ſtile.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is much Controverſie alſo concerning the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or firſt ſubject of the Power of the Keys,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> with the ſeveral proportions of power belonging reſpectively to the Presbytery, and to the Fraternity. A Subject worthy of deepeſt ſearch, and which accordingly hath exerciſed the thoughts and pens of many. But we hope in the Lord that this difference upon a ſevere Conſideration of it, will not be found ſo great, nor ſo difficult to be accommodated as may ſeem: for if there be, but a practical avoiding of the rocks and extreams on both hands, both of the Eccleſiaſtical Anarchy and confuſion on the one hand, and of Eccleſiaſtical Tyranny and oppreſſion on the other: If the Authority of the Elderſhip be ſecured that it be not devoured and ſwallowed up, by the Liberty of the Brotherhood, nor yet the Liberties of the Brethren by the power of the Elders, this is the ſubſtance of the matter, and in this we all agree:</p>
               <p>For Firſt it is agreed and granted by the <hi>Independents,</hi> that Chriſt hath placed the ruling power in the hands of his Officers only, and that the People are not the Rulers, but only the Ruled. For to make them all Rulers, and the Elders Cyphers, this is not the order of the Goſpel which ſaith <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves.</hi> Hebrews 13.17. <hi>And we beſeech you Brethren to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you; and eſteem them very highly in love for their works ſake, and be at peace among your ſelves.</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.12, 13. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to caſt aſide the fear and reverence of them and their Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo to give them but a painted power and empty titles, and to make them Rulers in name, but not in deed, this is ſuch a Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Goſpel order and caſting off the Yoke of Chriſt, as muſt needs break the Churches peace, and open a gap to all contention
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96320:8"/>and confuſion. Any ſuch exorbitant Independency of Carnal Liberty, and contentious confuſion, our Brethren of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional way, do neither plead for, nor practiſe, but diſavow and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim.</p>
               <p>And yet withal Secondly, it is agreed and granted by the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> that the People are not to behave themſelves as mere idle ſpectators, and perſons altogether unconcerned in Church matters, but that they ought ſome way to Concur and conſent at leaſt in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of chief weight and moment, as in the conſtituting of Officers, and in the receiving and ejecting of members, and conſequently that they are to be acquainted with ſuch tranſactions, to the end that if they have any thing to object or alledge, they may bring it in to the Elders to judge thereof. Thus much is granted and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed amongſt our Brethren of the Presbytery. So that if both theſe be put together, it will appear that here is ſome good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of practical Agreements, for which we are to bleſs God and to pray, that it may be further improved, though there may be ſome notional difference.</p>
               <p>He that ſhall peruſe and compare together Mr. <hi>Cotten</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> his Treatiſe of <hi>the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gillaspy</hi> of <hi>Scotland, his diſpute againſt Engliſh Popiſh Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> will find them both of one heart and mind, as to this ſignal inſtance of the Peoples power and priviledge, <hi>viz.</hi> the Right they have to Elect and chooſe their own Miniſters. And it is a Truth ſo clearly aſſerted in the Scriptures of Truth, for they chooſe Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. And in the choice of an Apoſtle they went very far, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.23. And they choſe Elders by ſuffrage in every Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>cum per juffragia creaſſent. Beza.</hi> And it is ſo abundantly and ſo conſtantly witneſſed by the Saints and Martyrs, and by all our Proteſtant Divines againſt the Papiſts, and by our Brethren and Fathers, the old <hi>Puritan Non-conformiſts</hi> in all their Books and writings againſt the Prelates, and ſealed with their manifold and faithful ſufferings, that now in this height of Goſpel light to relinquiſh it, would be a very retrograde motion in the work of Reformation, and bring the Sun as it were Ten degrees backward. And if any ſhall require and inſiſt upon the relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhment of it, we muſt ingeniouſly confeſs unto them, that we are loth to purchaſe our Union with them at ſuch a Price. We
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96320:9"/>muſt confeſs it upon his Account, who hath purchaſed the Liberties of his people with his own blood, and whoſe Royal Authority, and whoſe infinite wiſdom hath thought fit to ordain in his laſt Will and Teſtament; therefore the People may not, muſt not be utterly excluded, we cannot, we dare not yield thereunto, howſoever their Concurrence may be manifeſted and expreſſed, whether by lifting up of hands, or by ſilence, or by other ways of voting, either more explicitely, or more implicitely, according to the various Circumſtances, of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Places and Times, which may admit of ſome variety, and ſo far as the Rule admits of any Latitude, we would not be too ſevere and narrow. In the teſtimony before quoted out of the 39 Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and the Book of Common Prayer, which are owned and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed even by the Epiſcopal men, and by all the Conforming Clergy, there is reiterated and expreſs mention of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as intereſted and concerned in Church Affairs, both in the Secluſion of Impenitent Sinners, as Perſons by whom <hi>the Congregation is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended,</hi> and in the open declaration of their repentance, <hi>that ſo the Congregation may thereby be ſatisfied,</hi> and they readmitted.</p>
               <p>From all that hath been ſaid as to this head, we hope, we may come to this reſult, that if we could but underſtand one another, there needs no further expedient, for the compoſing and reconciling of this Controverſie.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is alſo ſome difference about the ſubject of Baptiſm, and the extent as to the external diſpenſation of the Covenant of Grace ſealed by it. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> conceiving that it belongeth to all that profeſs the Proteſtant Chriſtian Religion, and to their Children. The <hi>Independents</hi> reſtraining it only, to ſuch Parents as beſides their profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith walk without offence, and ſo are judged worthy of the Lords Supper, and to their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. The <hi>Anti-paedo baptiſts</hi> reſtraining it, yet further to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of all Infants, as from the Covenant, ſo likewiſe from the Seal thereof, as belonging in their judgments, only to perſons grown up to years of diſcretion upon their own perſonal profeſſion of the Faith. And indeed this difference though not ſo much debated and written of as the former about Claſſical ſubordinations and Church Power, yet being a matter of daily practice, doth incur more into the obſervation and underſtandings of the Common People. The
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96320:9"/>diſtance being very conſpicuous between this three-fold Judgment and practice of Baptiſing almoſt all the Children in the Nation, and none at all, and none but ſuch whole Parents are accepted as Godly unto full Communion.</p>
               <p>Here then be three ſeveral ways, the diſtance whereof is in ſome meaſure underſtood. But yet in the help of Chriſt, let us try how near they may be brought together, reducing the differences to the narroweſt point we can.</p>
               <p>Firſt Then, they that are counted largeſt, are not for Baptiſmal adminiſtrations abſolutely Univerſal, but they require a profeſſion of the true Chriſtian Faith at leaſt. Moreover the <hi>Independents,</hi> who are counted ſomewhat narrow in this matter, yet they do not monopolize and impropriate Baptiſm to themſelves, as though it belonged only to thoſe of their way: But they do profeſs and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that if the Parents be ſuch whoſe hearts God hath touched, though they walk not with us, if they be by other Saints and Miniſters with whom they walk, Judged Godly, and found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Lord's Supper for themſelves: They do acknowledge ſuch Parents, under what Form ſoever, to be worthy alſo of that Bleſſed priviledge of Baptiſm for their Children.</p>
               <p>But as to the Third opinion, that of the <hi>Anti-paedo-Baptiſts,</hi> here indeed lies the greateſt difficulty, becauſe it is thought by many, that in the true and unconſtrained Conſequences of it, it draws very deep, beſide all the Prejudices that have ariſen as to that Form, upon other pretenſions and occurrences, that have hapned both at home, and abroad, too many to be here enumerated. And that it is indeed a matter of deeper Comprehenſion in all the Influences and Concernments of it, than we can wade into at this time, we muſt ingenuouſly confeſs to our diſſenting Friends, but yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we muſt acknowledge alſo our want of light, and ability to evince and demonſtrate any of theſe three Judgements, to be in its own nature, if ſingly conſidered, and by itſelf, a fundamental errour. Therefore we humbly Judge that it is a duty incumbent on us in the Spirit of Goſpel Love to bear with one another in it, till it pleaſe the Father of Lights, out of his Free-Grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to ſhine in upon us, and upon our differing Brethren with fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and more Convicting light.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96320:10"/>
               <p>But here be ſome other Queſtions concerning this great and Bleſſed ordinance of Baptiſm, wherein both the other Forms do fully agree in one and the ſame mind and Judgment againſt the <hi>Anti-paedo-Baptiſts.</hi> And concerning the manner of Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which theſe conceive, ought to be by dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or plunging the Body under water.
<note place="margin">Confeſs. Anab. prop. 39.</note> The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> on the contrary hold that, <q>dipping of the Perſon into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not neceſſary,
<note place="margin">Confeſs. Faith Cap. of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm propos. 3.</note> but Baptiſm is rightly adminiſtred by powring or ſprinkling water upon the Perſon.</q> Alſo concerning the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator, the <hi>Anti-paedo-Baptiſts</hi> hold that it may be done by Diſciples, being men able to Preach the Goſpel.
<note place="margin">Confeſs. Anab. prop. 31.</note> But the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> concur that it doth belong peculiarly to the Office of the Miniſtry, and ought not to be diſpenſed, but by a Miniſter of the Goſpel lawfully Called.</p>
               <p>As for ſuch as make Baptiſm in their way the very Eſſence and Form of the Church, this is indeed to un-church all others beſide themſelves,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>R. L.</hi> of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſeparation.</note> and ſo puts a Bar upon Church Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them, as being no Churches; But the ſeverity of this diſ-uniting principle, as we cannot find it expreſly aſſerted in their Confeſſion of Faith before mentioned,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>H. L.</hi> of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</note> ſo we know ſome of that way who do diſown it, and affirm that Baptiſm doth not enter the definition of a Church, but they make Union and Communion with Chriſt the foundation of Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which as it is a more Scriptural, ſo it is a more Brotherly, and a more uniting principle.</p>
               <p>Theſe therefore are the main things in difference, and under diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute amongſt the three Forms, omitting only ſome few things which either ſeem to be of Leſſer moment, or cannot well be affixed to any of the three Forms or Parties, as the Judgment of the whole Party, or elſe are implyed and included in theſe which have been mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proposals">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96320:10"/>
               <head>Propoſals.</head>
               <p>And now having ſeen and taken this ſhort ſurvey of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies agitated amongſt profeſſors under theſe ſeveral Forms, we may with the more clearneſs proceed to conſider, whether there might not be ſome nearer cloſure and Union than yet hath been, and that without intrenching upon the different perſuaſions of each party. Doubtleſs there may, if our Spirits be not at a greater diſtance than our Principles.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing both the Agreements, and the Differences to be truly, and rightly ſtated, as to the main things in this which hath been ſaid, as we ſuppoſe all that underſtand them will readily acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the Agreements being ſo great and many, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences ſo few, that which we have to propoſe upon the whole is this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="query">
               <head>Quaery.</head>
               <p>Whether Union in ſo many great Truths, which in the Light and Grace of Chriſt, and in the Conduct of his Word and Spirit we have attained to, be not a ſufficient foundation for three things more.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For a mutual owning and giving the right hand of Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to each other as true Churches and Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, in whom ſomething of his grace and preſence doth appear, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thoſe leſſer differences before mentioned.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And conſequently to concern our ſelves in the Affairs of one
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96320:11"/>another, ſo far as to give mutual Advice and Aſſiſtance as occaſion may require. And,</p>
               <p n="3">3. To receive the Approved Members of each others Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to occaſion all Communion in the Lords Supper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>We humbly conceive with ſubmiſſion to better Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that theſe Queries may be anſwered in the Affirmative. And that the greatneſs of the Agreements, and the ſmallneſs of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences before evinced by ſuch a particular Induction, is a Baſis and a ground work firm enough, whereon to demonſtrate not only the poſſibility, but the neceſſity of our Uniting. Whereunto theſe Motives beſide many others may perſuade.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It cannot be denied, but that ſuch as agree in all thoſe great principles of Truth before mentioned, if alſo their Lives and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations be without offence are viſible Saints, or Godly Perſons in the Judgment of rational Charity. And certainly it is the duty of Saints to unite and come as near together as they can, and to receive one another, as Chriſt alſo received us to the Glory of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.7. Corrupt Aſſociations and mixtures of Profeſſors with Men viſibly wicked and ungodly, the Scripture every where teſtifies againſt. But the Perſons of whom we treat, are to humane Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to outward appearance, Saints, yea, Confeſſors and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſufferers in the cauſe of Chriſt, than which there cannot be a greater Indearment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If ever there be a time and ſeaſon for it, wherein the Lord calls his people to it, to ſtudy Union and lamenting their former diſtances and offences, to ſeek peace and purſue it, ſurely it is at ſuch a time, when he hath brought them all into a ſuffering Condition together, under the preſſures and yoaks of men upon upon their Conſciences. It is time then to lay aſide their mutual animoſities, and to learn that <hi>Golden Rule,</hi> Rom. 14.3. <hi>Let not him that eateth, deſpiſe him which eateth not, and let not him which eateth not Judge him that eateth, for God hath received him.</hi> A
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96320:11"/>Golden Rule of Chriſtian Love, the ſenſe whereof may be thus rendred in the Aſpect, it beareth to the diſputations of our Times. Let not him that dependeth in the way of Claſſical ſubordination, deſpiſe him that dependeth not, and let not him that dependeth not Judge him that dependeth, for God hath received him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is no ſelling Truth to purchaſe peace. There is no ſuch dead fly in the Ointment. There is no ſilencing or ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of any Truth of God by theſe Propoſals, nor any tendency we hope to ſcepticiſm, or perſonal Indifferency in the things of his Houſe and Worſhip, whereunto that good principle of tenderneſs and moderation towards Brethren of differing Judgments, hath been by ſome either unskilfully, or perverſely miſimproved. Which Form ſoever hath the mind of Chriſt, and the Truth on their ſide, here is nothing doth ſo far intrench upon them, but that they may freely hold it forth, they may retain and practiſe that wherein they differ, according to their preſent Convictions, notwithſtanding this degree of Union, and ſo neither is any truth ſuppreſſed, nor any ones Conſcience impoſed upon.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yea, if we could thus far unite, as it would conduce through the Grace of Chriſt to a further increaſe of Love, ſo likewiſe to the further diſcovery and clearing up of the Truth in thoſe things wherein we differ, by vertue of that promiſe, Phil. 3.15, 16. <hi>If in anything ye be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal even this unto you, nevertheleſs whereto we have attained, let us walk by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. It would in ſome meaſure remove that great ſtumbling block from before the blind prophane world, who pretend to take of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at our diviſions, looking upon them in the multiplying Glaſſes of their own enmity, and ſo accounting every difference in Religion to be a different Religion. But who knows how Convincing this might be to them, according to the Lord's prayer for his Diſciples, John. 17.21, 23. <hi>That they all may be one, as thou Father art in me and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us, that the world may believe that thou haſt ſent me.</hi> Doubtleſs it will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96320:12"/>Convince ſuch as belong to the Election of his Grace, ſo as to bring them in, and the reſt will be left the more without excuſe. And finally it will rejoice them that <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> and be pleaſing unto him whoſe name is called upon us, and who hath ſo often Commanded us <hi>To love one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:96320:12"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
